<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:random</id><updated>Wed Jan 13 00:00:00 UTC 2016</updated><title type="text">Yo! Briefcase: random</title><link rel="self" href="https://yobriefca.se/feed/random.xml"></link><entry><title>entr</title><updated>Wed Jan 13 00:00:00 UTC 2016</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2016/01/13/entr/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:entr</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://entrproject.org/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;entr&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a command line utility for running arbitrary commands when files change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just for clarification - I did not contribute to this project. I just happen to find it useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, yes you already have all this with guard, live-reload, guardian, watcher, watchy, watch, bouncy, bounce, bouncer, sir-loads-alot, loady, loadup, springy, trampoline, hot-rocket&lt;a name="_1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; etc. but &lt;a href="http://entrproject.org/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;entr&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is worth a look. Why? Well it has a few criteria that make it compelling,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It's not locked into a particular use case, language or ecosystem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has no external dependencies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It works on more than just Linux&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It's command line friendly (works with pipes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;So lets just see it in action,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Install it&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can either build it from &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/eradman/entr/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt; or if you're using a mac you an use brew&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="bash"&gt;brew update &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; brew install entr
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Use it&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What you want to do is get a list of files you are interested in i.e. ones that should trigger "something" when they change. This can be something as simple as &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; or as convoluted as &lt;code&gt;find . -iname '*.cr' -not -path './.crystal/*'&lt;/code&gt; something like. One way or another a command that spits out a file list is the first part.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next you pipe this into &lt;code&gt;entr&lt;/code&gt; with the command you want to run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="bash"&gt;ls -d * | entr make
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this case when a file listed by &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; changes &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; will be ran.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Further betterness&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is good enough for many use cases but there are always edge cases. One good example is live reloading a web server. In this case the process that you spawn typically blocks until killed which would cause issues with the above command. To cater for this use case &lt;code&gt;entr&lt;/code&gt; gives us the &lt;code&gt;-r&lt;/code&gt; flag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="bash"&gt;ls -d * | entr -r lein ring server-headless
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;code&gt;-r&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;entr&lt;/code&gt; will attempt to terminate then running process prior to starting it again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also have the &lt;code&gt;-c&lt;/code&gt; option. This does nothing more than clear the screen before running the command.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;code&gt;entr&lt;/code&gt; provides the ability to pass a special argument, &lt;code&gt;/_&lt;/code&gt;, into the command it is configured to run. This argument will be replaced with the path to the first file that has changed. This is useful when you specifically need to execute the changed file, for example, when working with data loading scripts,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code class="bash"&gt;ls ./data/*.js | entr mongo &amp;lt; /_
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://entrproject.org/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;entr&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is nice and simple with no external dependencies and not specific to any particular technology stack. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name="1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#_1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;: I may have made some or all of these up.&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Isolation</title><updated>Wed Jun 24 00:00:00 UTC 2015</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2015/06/24/isolation/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:Isolation</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One morning you woke up and things were different. Not hugely different - just ever so slightly. Almost imperceptibly so. You didn't really notice it at first but eventually you felt that something seemed "off". You had got up, had breakfast, brushed your teeth, cycled to work, showered, made a coffee and sat down at your desk and you just sensed it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you remember when you were a kid and you lost one of your favourite toys but found it again months later after having given up on the search. Did you ever get that weird sensation that it was much smaller, maybe less detailed than you remember? Well you're getting that feeling now, the space around you just "feels" smaller. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a while you notice it. A wall. That wall wasn't there before - you are sure of it. It doesn't actually look new; in fact it doesn't even look out of place but you're positive it wasn't there before.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next week, while going to another floor in the office to visit a work colleague, you notice another strange thing. One of the office doors isn't there anymore. As far as you recall there used to be another office between those two doors on the far wall, you'd had a meeting there once and you would swear to it. Other people don't seem bothered - "it looks the same to me" they say - and it's not as if there is evidence of some fresh plastering in the space. It just seems, well, smaller.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the next few months to a year little things like this happen. You notice, or at least feel, that things are getting smaller. There is less space to move around and even more widely there are less people occupying the space. Even places you've never been before feel significantly more constrained. There are people you haven't spoken in a while, you don't miss these people immediately because they aren't a really part of your core pack of people you see on a regular basis, but you did sense them missing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the moments you take to reflect on your life you notice just how small everything is getting. How compact, how claustrophobic everything is. Basic math tells you that there must be more space between these walls but there are no doors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One day you wake up and go to your office but looking around you're not even sure how you really got there. There are no other doors just the one door from your house to your office.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You feel alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Isolation can happen for many reasons both internal and external. The reasons can be anything from mental state, actions to something as simple as an inflexible and strongly held opinion. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals become isolated a team does not, not as readily at least. Teams, genuine teams of people that care about each other and the work they do, create an internal supportive culture. Individuals problems can be diminished through collective support. Toxic attitudes can be identified and a resolution can be reached.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the same way a toxic attitude does not thrive in a strong team, a good team cannot thrive in an unsupportive or constrained organisational culture be it in a company or community. We may talk about how culture is important but I don't think we all consider what that means. Being inclusive and supportive requires real effort at all levels of an organisation.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Don't Call It A Comeback</title><updated>Wed Apr 29 00:00:00 UTC 2015</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2015/04/29/dont-call-it-a-comeback/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:Don't Call It A Comeback</id><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Taking a break is only a break if you get back into it. Otherwise thats just retiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Activity on this site has declined recently. Initially it was intentional (in 2014 I decided to reduce my speaking engagements and focus on contracting), take a break, clear the head etc. but I got sidetracked and kept meaning to get back to a bit of writing and speaking. This proved harder than usual. Travelling every week kind of knocks the wind out of you, or me at least.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an effort to shine a light on the lack of activity I created a &lt;a href="http://yobriefca.se/metrics"&gt;contribution chart&lt;/a&gt; to show the drop off and, interestingly enough, I've been in a bit of a dip since before I actively decided to take a break. Or perhaps I'm just finding my rhythm. Or perhaps consistency isn't my strong point, you know like MongoDB.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyway the plan is to get back at it, talk more, write more and rant more. I've missed it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the interested the &lt;a href="http://yobriefca.se/metrics"&gt;contribution chart&lt;/a&gt; was thrown together using &lt;a href="http://d3js.org/"&gt;D3&lt;/a&gt; a hacked version of the &lt;a href="http://bl.ocks.org/mbostock/4063318"&gt;calendar view example&lt;/a&gt; and CSV data generated every time this site generates.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Operation Sprint Finish</title><updated>Sun Oct 05 00:00:00 UTC 2014</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2014/10/05/operation-sprint-finish/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:Operation Sprint Finish</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few months back I closed off a busy period. Between normal 9-5 working and running some &lt;a href="http://yobriefca.se/talks/"&gt;workshops and talks&lt;/a&gt;, I didn't have much free to devote to side projects and my writing. As soon as things died down I was ready to dive into all those ideas that I had logged and pushed to the back of my mind. Thats about as far as I got. Thinking. Little to no action, and even when I did muster the motivation to actually start something I either got distracted with a different; fresher idea or over thought the problem so hard that I either reduced it to something that already exists or over complicated it that it lost the appeal. A lot of these are signs of burnout so I decided to take some time to clear my head. I've done little to no blogging, accidentally ran a &lt;a href="http://yobriefca.se/presentations/functional-programming-with-clojure.pdf"&gt;Clojure workshop&lt;/a&gt; and generally thought about how to approach the problem of tackling my ideas rather than the ideas themselves.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am now into my third week of what I've playfully dubbed &lt;strong&gt;Operation Sprint Finish&lt;/strong&gt; and the reason why I'm talking about this now is that this week is my writing week - a week purely devoted to writing about all those topics I have listed in Wunderlist (though not necessarily publishing everything this week). Based on the last 2 weeks I've genuinely made decent progress on two of my personally important ideas than I did prior to having structure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So what is &lt;strong&gt;Operation Sprint Finish&lt;/strong&gt;? Well I first started by listing as many of the ideas I've had as possible (I ended up with about 20 or so that I really wanted to tackle). Next I selected 5 of these and designated them as &lt;strong&gt;immediate&lt;/strong&gt; and the rest as &lt;strong&gt;sometime in the future&lt;/strong&gt;. Well technically I selected 6 but that also includes the ever present &lt;strong&gt;writing, screencasting and presenting&lt;/strong&gt; work (which all fall under the same high level category - or if you're into agile buzzwords - &lt;strong&gt;epic&lt;/strong&gt;). These main ideas are the first batch of ideas I want to take as far as I logically can before I determine them either redundant or release them in some form. From these six epics I generated a list of things that need done and could be done reasonably within a one week period. Most of these were marked as &lt;strong&gt;Idea XYZ Sprint #1&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Idea ABC Sprint #1&lt;/strong&gt; etc. with some overarching objectives and goals. Then using &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.random.org/"&gt;REALSCIENCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; I picked one of the items and moved that into play for the next week/sprint.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For one week I focus squarely on that task. If new things come up they go on the backlog, new ideas go on the &lt;strong&gt;sometime in the future&lt;/strong&gt; list (or swapped with one of the &lt;strong&gt;immediate&lt;/strong&gt; epics as there can be only 6). At the end of the week I leave a comment (I'm using &lt;a href="http://trello.com"&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt; to orchestrate all this) on the epic so that I can pick up any future tasks quickly and pick my next item. In fact I seem to find picking the tasks for the next 2 weeks at once a rather nice incentive as I know what to look forward to.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From the first two weeks I've managed to build&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A slightly more opinionated &lt;a href="http://www.luminusweb.net"&gt;Luminus&lt;/a&gt; project structure that gives me a great starting point for the app I was working on as well as future web apps using a Clojure stack.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A semicomplete prototype for an Android app (using Kotlin which was a pleasure) and a lot of design ideas for the app which was very frustrating but also rather fulfiling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both of these weeks have resulted in results that are far more complete than I've managed in recent times.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/blog/operation-sprint-finish.png" alt="Operation Sprint Finish" _="_" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And now this week I can start putting some articles on my site that I've been itching to talk about for a while. Perhaps even record this screencast I've been threating to do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I've done is allow myself to not be distracted, not talk myself out of an idea because the idea on the the other side is greener and worst case, should I hit a hard part (like how to approach the user experience of the mobile app I'm working on) I don't just give up and instead think it through and potentially crack it (which I think I did).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indeed I expect many people to be saying "So what? You're just applying the agile-y stuff to getting side projects done" and thats true but I still think there is value in writing about it. Besides, at the very least, this article still counts towards my current sprint deliverable which I guess is something, right?&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Nomadic Tendencies</title><updated>Thu Jul 24 00:00:00 UTC 2014</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2014/07/24/nomadic-tendencies/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:Nomadic Tendencies</id><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The future came and went in the mildly discouraging way that futures do."&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Neil Gaiman, Good Omens: The Nice and Accurate Prophecies of Agnes Nutter, Witch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If there is one thing that shows the immaturity of the software industry (relative to other industries) it's the ever present need to jump to the next big technology. Tales of "leaving X for Y" dot the path from one trend to the next. "I'm so much more productive in Y over X" is the battle cry of the newly indoctrinated acolytes of Y. Vast swathes of half finished, abandoned open source projects written in X collect dust in their respective repositories sitting alongside new shiny half-finished, soon to be abandoned open source projects written in Y. And the industry marches on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And yet most software that we use is still awful. It still exhibits the same problems, it still breaks in the most unpredictable ways and it leaves people as angry and frustrated as ever.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But I guess that's to be expected. If we regularly reinvent everything in "the next big thing" when do we ever find time to refine anything? The industry marches on, but the industry never moves. Like a perpetual early beta phase our systems are built up just enough before we tear them down and rewrite them in something new. Even enterprises, who tend to move much slower and are therefore buffered from smaller fluctuations in trend, suffer from the same problems at a different scale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ultimately this behavior puts the focus on the technology and how it can make our systems better. Our users are once more second class citizens because what &lt;strong&gt;we&lt;/strong&gt; want is somehow more important (and who needs users anyway when people are throwing millions at pointless smoke and mirror apps).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the problem is not the technology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem is that we are in love with our tools when we should be in love with our users. We need to talk to our users more and less to our peers. Spend less time on Hacker News debating stuff you only partially understand and try and get a better insight into how you can use your current, very pedestrian, technology stack to genuinely improve the lives of your users.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Estimates as Deadlines and the End of Everything</title><updated>Thu Jun 19 00:00:00 UTC 2014</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2014/06/19/estimates-as-deadlines-and-the-end-of-everything/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:Estimates as Deadlines and the End of Everything</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;"If you guess how many USB sticks are in the jar you win an iPad" they said with a smile that had been seared into their face from years of standing at conference popup stands selling the same message.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I glance over at the sacred prize. For randomly picking a number out of thin air I could easily walk away with a brand spanking new...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Wait", I say noticing something is odd about the prize. "Is that, an original iPad?".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Well its not a knock off it that's what you mean"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"No no I mean is it an original version, an iPad one?"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Oh, yep it is"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"And that's what you win?"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Of course"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Why are you giving away an ancient iPad?"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Well no one has ever actually won so we haven't felt the need to replace it"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Why has no one ever won?"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Well no one has ever guessed the exact amount of 1GB USB sticks in this jar"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"So you need to be exact, not just be 'the closest'?"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Of course, now listen buddy, are you just going to question me about the prize or are you going to listen while I talk to you about our latest release of Super Pro Manager 4.0 - Agile Enterprise Edition."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I walk off, its not even worth the effort. I'd either need a the historical data of guesses or a chance to take each stick out and count them individually. Even then the prize at the end of it is completely out of line with what I'd expected in the first place - a &lt;strong&gt;new&lt;/strong&gt; iPad.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The Cold Hard Truth&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The story above sounds incredibly silly yet we as an industry still do this on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm still hearing, to this day, stories of people treating estimates as targets. I'm hearing them from the enterprise companies that will never change and I'm hearing them from the companies that grace our stages at conferences and talk about how they are "enabling agile teams to deliver value by running lean with a shared responsibility".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reality is many teams are forced into this fixed template of Scrum with its overhead of extra ceremony and expected to deliver more without giving up the practices of old. It's crunch time every sprint for the team. Its unsustainable. We see the senior members "rise up" and become "cross team" conduits for best practice and status updates. They have successfully extracted themselves from the daily grind and frustration of the sprint.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It may sound like just another one of those developer frustrations that managers tell us "same as it ever was, back in my day..." ad nauseam - but it's not. When we combine it with the faux-agile, process over people, approach most organisations actually have then we have a serious problem. Seriouser, in fact. The teams that were already shipping software in a healthy manner continue to do that, the ones who changed over the last few years in response to careful agile marketering and brand engagement (through certification and top dollar coaching) have just heaped more pain onto their process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The iterative and incremental application of big design upfront methodology practices will completely and utterly dehumanise a team. People begin to tell themselves that the flat team, the shared vision, one goal stuff was nonsense anyway, it pays the bills for the houses and flats they never really get to see because of the "Unending Project Death March" being exacted one overladen, overprocess-ised, overtime driven sprint at a time. The team don't get their 3 months head space of building solutions against slipping timelines followed by a few weeks of intense crunching, no, they get a constant slightly less intense crunching &lt;strong&gt;all the time&lt;/strong&gt;, non-stop, forever and ever and ever and ever and ever.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don't believe me? Trust me this is so widespread, so pandemic, that one musical collective even wrote a song about it - &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-aLjup934Rk"&gt;Godspeed You! Black Emperor - The Dead Flag Blues&lt;/a&gt;. Of course they had to give it a fictional political lean to avoid getting into trouble at work but at the risk of getting them found out allow me to break their brutally honest piece down a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The car is on fire, and there's no driver at the wheel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And the sewers are all muddied with a thousand lonely suicides&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And a dark wind blows&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is every IT project. Ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government is corrupt&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And we're on so many drugs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the radio on and the curtains drawn&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The "government", yeah right, more like a cheeky nod to managment and sales. The drugs are Scrum and Agile and we are listening to the things these people say without looking outside our walls following our estimates and hoping it will all be different this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;We're trapped in the belly of this horrible machine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And the machine is bleeding to death&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Public and private money spent on failing systems across every industry and we are all just cogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sun has fallen down&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And the billboards are all leering&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And the flags are all dead at the top of their poles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flags are the principles we once felt we stood for - making a difference, changing the world, all dead or dying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It went like this:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The buildings tumbled in on themselves&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mothers clutching babies&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Picked through the rubble&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And pulled out their hair&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Buildings clearly represents the promises and contracts based on estimates. The fallout of these being wrong are clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The skyline was beautiful on fire&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All twisted metal stretching upwards&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Everything washed in a thin orange haze&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;At some point you start to accept that this is as good as it gets. You're immune to the mess, in love with the decimation you and your contemporaries have wrought. But its all still broken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I said, "Kiss me, you're beautiful -&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are truly the last days"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You grabbed my hand&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And we fell into it&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like a daydream&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Or a fever&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;You give up, you go with it, you accept that broken is the only thing this can ever be. You allow yourself to believe this, you forget everything you ever cared about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;We woke up one morning and fell a little further down&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For sure it's the valley of death&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;You adopt a new technology, a new platform, you let it consume you, you raise your rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I open up my wallet&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And it's full of blood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consultancy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;The End of Everything&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;It may have seemed like a small thing to enforce estimates as targets but you've just ruined the world a bit more. Your teams write crappy broken software because they hate what they do. They hate what we do because they are forced to work against arbitrary timescales like battery chickens - no light, hemmed in pushing out sub-standard cheap bits of code as often as possible. Quantity over quality, no time for quality, no way no how.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the end of everything.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>On onpaste</title><updated>Thu May 08 00:00:00 UTC 2014</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2014/05/08/on-onpaste/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:On onpaste</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When they say,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;We'd lose our security certificate if we allowed pasting [into &lt;code&gt;input&lt;/code&gt; fields]. It could leave us open to a "brute force" attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;They forget that their webpage is simply a client of their backend service. There are many other &lt;a href="http://www.getpostman.com/"&gt;existing ones&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They forget that stopping "brute force" attacks is a matter for their back end.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They forget that JavaScript can be disabled, fail to load or used to turn off 'onpaste'.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They forget that these practices force their customers to use simpler passwords&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They forget that their actions make their customers more vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They forget that when a user, who was for all intents and purposes forced by them to use a simple guessable password, has their account compromised they use words that put the blame on that user and make them feel bad. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I say &lt;em&gt;forget&lt;/em&gt; but I really mean &lt;em&gt;ignore the fact&lt;/em&gt;. I guess it's easier to hide behind outdated words and policy than understand the &lt;strong&gt;needs of the user&lt;/strong&gt;, your customers.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>So Long, and Thanks for All the Code</title><updated>Thu Jan 02 00:00:00 UTC 2014</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2014/01/02/so-long-and-thanks-for-all-the-code/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:So Long, and Thanks for All the Code</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;2014 is going to be a bit different. At the tail end of 2013 I decided to hand in and work out my notice with &lt;a href="http://kainos.com"&gt;Kainos&lt;/a&gt;. So from February onwards I'll be doing a spot of contracting, validating a few business ideas and generally seeing how I can benefit the tech community in and around Belfast as a free agent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently the cost of being a full time employee in a company that is growing rapidly has outweighed the value I've drawn from it and committing to another year wouldn't have been the right decision for me. So, instead, I'll be giving up the warm comforting embrace of full time employment with a company that has given me plenty of support through the years to rough it in the wilds of the tech industry. Hopefully this move will offer me greater flexibility and control in what I do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of now it seems I'm going to be pretty busy for the first part of the year but if there is anything commercial or even community related you feel I could help with (this site should tell you &lt;a href="/background"&gt;everything you need to know&lt;/a&gt;) don't hesitate to &lt;a href="mailto://james@yobriefca.se"&gt;contact me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>biomatic - Twitter Bio Generator for Realz!</title><updated>Thu Nov 07 00:00:00 UTC 2013</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="http://biomatic.herokuapp.com/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:biomatic - Twitter Bio Generator for Realz!</id><content type="html"></content></entry><entry><title>Elsewhere</title><updated>Wed Jun 05 23:00:00 UTC 2013</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2013/06/05/elsewhere/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:Elsewhere</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Oh hey hi, this post is a "personal" post. It doesn't involve any code or analogies to writing software (that I'm aware of) so yeah.....&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many many years ago (well about 9 or 10) I went through a period of "being a singer/song-writer". There was no intention of making money or even playing live - I can barely speak to people I &lt;strong&gt;don't&lt;/strong&gt; know let alone "perform" in front of them (though I can waffle about technical stuff Ad nauseam - oh the irony) - I just felt compelled to record some noise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Experiment #1&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first time I did it was for my sister, a born and bred muso, as a birthday present - she had moved to London a few years ago and I wrote a song about her being always "busy".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fapi.soundcloud.com%2Ftracks%2F95763666"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The quality is clearly terrible, the song is clearly terrible, I am clearly terrible. But dear readers - hello - this is me. Was me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyway. I quite liked the process of recording - one maybe, two takes, no editing. I hated hearing my voice and shambling guitar but I did like the fact something existed that I created.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Experiment #2&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;After that I did a little experiment. The idea was this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drink for an hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Record an hour of music (one take)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drink for an hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Record an hour of music (one take)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5 and 6 and 7 and 8 follow a similar pattern.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width="100%" height="450" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fapi.soundcloud.com%2Fplaylists%2F6460430"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That was awesome because it was, for me, kind of wild and cool and if I ever put any thought into anything I hate it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Experiment #3&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also out of the previous process I got enough rough recording to do an Extended Play of music I genuinely like to this day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width="100%" height="450" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fapi.soundcloud.com%2Fplaylists%2F6459707"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was a cathartic post - I did things, and yeah I do things.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>trello-printer - Print cards from Trello boards</title><updated>Fri May 24 00:00:00 UTC 2013</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="http://yobriefca.se/trello-printer/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:trello-printer - Print cards from Trello boards</id><content type="html"></content></entry><entry><title>Quitsies, Well Sort Of</title><updated>Mon Jul 02 23:00:00 UTC 2012</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2012/07/02/quitsies-well-sort-of/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:Quitsies, Well Sort Of</id><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;You know when you start to question why you write these things it's probably time to quit, or at least take a break. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;~ me, just there now&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This more of an FYI to anyone who may read this blog than a horrible diatribe about how I am wasting my life with meaningless exercises or technologies I'll never get to use to a bunch of people that don't really care, what would be the point? Plus - it's probably not even true. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So rather than pottering on about cool and interesting technologies that will make everyones (read, developers) life infinitely better 100% guaranteed I've decided to devote my time to, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working on some startup-py type things that have been milling around the back of my head for some time, and,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generally getting stuff done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yep, like a hipster band, this little testament to bike-shedding is going on indefinite hiatus.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>5 Years</title><updated>Fri May 25 23:00:00 UTC 2012</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2012/05/25/5-years/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:5 Years</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I am sitting here, here being London - 315(ish) miles away from my family, halfway through the &lt;a href="http://nhshackday.com"&gt;NHS Hack Day&lt;/a&gt; and having a bit of a personal crisis. I often have these little episodes but this one has been languishing in my dusty old head for a good while - refusing to go away, nagging me every time I have a chance to ponder things. It's the same old thing - why am I doing any of this stuff I do? I don't generally get a great amount of opportunity in work to really stretch my creative urges. That sort of thing happens on my own time and therefore given my other responsibilities (my wife, family and lifes associated activities) is done under a fairly tight deadline. Add this to the fact I bore easily of things that aren't really benefiting people immediately - I tend to flit, easily, between little unfinished projects. But wait.... I did it again. You see back there, about 2 sentences ago I just sidelined my entire life. Thrown between two looming brackets I relegated my wife and family to a byline yet again. Oy vey.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And this brings me, neatly enough, to the point of this entire ramble.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Five years ago I married my awesome wife and in that time I've done a heap of things - relocated twice, had two kids bought a house, got promoted, pissed everyone off, seen a few countries and bought/traded three cars (which get smaller every time oddly enough). And through all this hopping around my wife has been the one true constant. She thinks, most of the time, I don't care about her - after all I'm in London participating in a hackathon on our 5th wedding anniversary because I stupidly didn't put two and two together and notice the clash. So yeah it may damn well seem like she comes in a close second to my hobby/career stuff (you know the stuff I already mentioned was pulling into crisis mode). But it's not true. I can't help the fact I am "emotionally retarded", as my sister once called it, but perhaps once in a while I really should let her know that she means more than she thinks she does. And here it is. A little bit of emotional letting if you will.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dear Emma - happy anniversary, I hope we have plenty more, thank you for putting up with me, you're aces.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>The Little Sacrifices</title><updated>Sat Apr 28 23:00:00 UTC 2012</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2012/04/28/the-little-sacrifices/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:The Little Sacrifices</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Late night ramblings... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Productivity can plateau very quickly - especially in a technical process. No matter how good you get at the process or approach, if you keep doing the same thing you can only get so good at it or do it so fast. It's possible, however, by sacrificing some of your precious time to go beyond that plateau. There are things we, the developers, do as part of our development process that are so small and insignificant that we do them without thinking&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clearing down the values in LocalStorage when debugging a web app&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copying assets from one folder to another (aka the macgyver deploy)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Navigating to &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:8000&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;9000&lt;/code&gt; or some other port&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Typing &lt;code&gt;rake generate preview&lt;/code&gt; into the terminal about 20 times an hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;These are but a few things I've had to consider today alone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generally these things are so small we'd just do them by hand, right? But if you take the time to automate these processes or even just refine them in some way it can do wonders for you productivity going forward.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example the clearing of LocalStorage in Chrome - spent a few minutes writing a bookmarklet that you can execute with 1 click. The macgyver deploy? Write a rake/make/jake/psake/cake task for it. Better yet use &lt;a href="https://github.com/guard/guard"&gt;Guard&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://github.com/mynyml/watchr"&gt;Watchr&lt;/a&gt; and perform the deploy on save! Navigatin to various different localhost ports? Try my &lt;a href="http://yobriefca.se/blog/2012/04/03/alfred-hack-for-web-developers/"&gt;alfred script&lt;/a&gt; to minimise the keystrokes. &lt;code&gt;rake generate preview&lt;/code&gt; - alias that bad boy to &lt;code&gt;rgp&lt;/code&gt;! Save yourself those extra keystrokes - you might need them later.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Listen - specifics aren't important here. You'll have your own small repetitive tasks and you'll be able to find your own ways to automate, improve or refine them - but this is the point. You probably don't. At least not as often as you should. Losing a second here and there on one task means very little in the small. In the large, across many of these tasks, well thats a different story. It's hard to justify spending 10 or 20 minutes on something to automate a task that takes 5 seconds to run but even if the time doesn't repay for a while then the fact you have less of a cognitive shift between your primary task and this secondary one should allow you stay in the highly effective, productive mindset to get the job done. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So give it a go, even as a thought experiment - think about the habitual development tasks you do and how you could automate them - you could well suprise yourself (like I have been recently).&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Alfred Hack for Web Developers</title><updated>Mon Apr 02 23:00:00 UTC 2012</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2012/04/02/alfred-hack-for-web-developers/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:Alfred Hack for Web Developers</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been a fan of &lt;a href="http://www.alfredapp.com/"&gt;Alfred&lt;/a&gt; for some time and use it to make pretty much everything a keystroke away. I've thrown a very small little extension that reduces the time to jump between console and newly started web app. Generally during development we need to run our app jump to &lt;code&gt;localhost:PORT&lt;/code&gt; and make sure it's working. If, like me, you have a lot of different apps and platforms (Scala, Jekyll, Rails, Sinatra, Express to name a few) then &lt;code&gt;PORT&lt;/code&gt; becomes the one thing you always need to type and the browsers auto predict is generally not that helpful in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alfred to the rescue here, just create a script as shown below and then running alfred and typing &lt;code&gt;l 9000&lt;/code&gt; you can launch your default browser at &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:9000&lt;/code&gt;. Very simple but saves me heaps of time at the minute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/blog/alfredscript.png" alt="Screenshot" _="_" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Done Spoked at DevWeek</title><updated>Tue Mar 27 23:00:00 UTC 2012</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2012/03/27/done-spoked-at-devweek/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:Done Spoked at DevWeek</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I made it through my talk at DevWeek which might sound a little odd but it took a whole bottle of cough syrup to do it. Not having been sick for most of the winter my body decided a day before DevWeek to go into shut down. I spent Tuesday in bed with very little voice. Thankfully the head colds hold on my vocal chords relented this morning and I think I managed to project as best I could. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So initial thoughts of how it went? I honestly think I'm getting better at this presenting thing so that must be a good thing, unless I was TERRIBLE before. The 2 main annoyances that have been raised thus far have been&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;1. Too Short&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I did my usual "talk really fast and finish earlier than planned" thing I sometimes do. But there was plenty of discussion afterwards which I tought was interesting. FWIW when I present this to myself it takes longer. My internal monologue must be slower than the way I speak. Apologies to anyone that felt it was "too short".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;2. Not enough Visual Studio&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I opted to play it safe end embed code into my slides rather than code live - I didn't go unnoticed and I had a few comments that "moar codez" would have been good. Totally agree. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Other Stuff&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I opted to change my slide deck between submitting them for print and presenting. I did it out of desire to devlier a better, more structured, talk (my first set being quite short as I was going for a "free-form" type of presentation). Probably not the most professional approach to do this but at least I can say my heart was in the right place :) Here are offending articles BTW&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="max-width:500px;margin:0 auto;"&gt;
	&lt;script src="http://speakerdeck.com/embed/4f719e7aca692c002101c187.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Code that was presented is available, as always, in/on my &lt;a href="https://github.com/kouphax/bddindotnet-code"&gt;Github Repo&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks to all who attended and any other feedback you have throw it my way so I can get better at this talking malarky.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also thanks to the folks at DevWeek for the opportunity - hopefully you'll have me back at some point.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>The Estimation 4x4</title><updated>Sun Feb 12 00:00:00 UTC 2012</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2012/02/12/the-estimation-4x4/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:The Estimation 4x4</id><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This post is dedicated to one of the most influential managers I've ever had the pleasure to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm of the opinion that the moment you start trying to apply complex mathematical rigour and time to estimation you've entered into a broken system. You're wasting time trying to protect yourself from finger pointing managers or getting a kicking from old school "us or them" lawyer types. None of that adds anything to the project except a big stick to beat people with and make sure they work themselves to death based a a random stab in the dark that is somehow made more realistic by the application if science. Ultimately though if the initial guesswork is wrong, and it's seldom on the nose, the science means sweet FA. So why bother? You're pleasing the wrong people. But then those people hold a lot of power. So as long as we can keep them happy with the minimum of effort life should be sweet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The Answer&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen I bring you the &lt;strong&gt;Estimation 4x4&lt;/strong&gt; - guaranteed to knock those super science estimation techniques out of the park.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The Science Bit&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Got a project to estimate? I've done your homework for you - &lt;strong&gt;4 people, 4 weeks&lt;/strong&gt;. BOOM! Mind Blown! Now get on with delivering that project buddy. Oh wait it's a big ass project - 4 people, 4 months. Oh wait you're limited by deadlines and/or resourcing - adjust as needed (3 people, 5 weeks or 5 people, 3 weeks).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Balancing Act&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Careful now, 9 women dont make a baby in 1 month so don't assume that scaling one side up to cater for the other will get the same results. Theres a balance that needs addressed. This is real science after all - repsect the rule and the rule will respect you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;You Gotta Be Kidding Me&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dont believe me? Try it out next time. Do your pseudo-scientific enterprise-ready finger in the air analysis. But hey see when that project is finished see how close the 4x4 would have brought you to the real result. I bet 9 times out of 10 it was as accurate as your real estimate, except you could have started much sooner....&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;#winning&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Standing at the cusp of 2011... WTF?</title><updated>Fri Dec 30 00:00:00 UTC 2011</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2011/12/30/standing-at-the-cusp-of-2011-dot-dot-dot-wtf/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:Standing at the cusp of 2011... WTF?</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure where this post is going to go in terms of content. I'm thinking a bit of full disclosure might be quite cathartic but at the same time do you really want to know the ins and out of my somewhat awful 2011? Compromise - I'll keep it short. Possibly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;2011 (The Bad Parts)&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;2011 was a pretty terrible year if I'm honest. It was the year my wife suffered two miscarriages, I got into my first car accident, stuff kept breaking and I totally dropped the ball in work when I burnt out (I'm certain I'm still feeling the effects of that). Oh and yes on top of all that I was diagnosed with severe depression for which I am now fully medicated. But you know what? I'm not alone - I know a ton of people for whom (look at me I said whom - how posh) 2011 was grim.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So lets cast aside all the personal stuff, we've all had our problems, and let me talk about the burn out. Long and short of it was that I took too much work on and eventually delivered unacceptable results for them all. I have something akin to ADD when it comes to work and unless I am suitably challenged or stimulated my productivity drops to pretty much nil. 2011 was full of time consuming mundane boring work for me and as I tried desperately to pull personal value from the work (or hobbies) I started making mistakes, over committing and generally under achieving. Lesson learned - I need to learn to say no and sometimes I just need to suck up the fact that we can't all be doing the best part of our jobs ALL THE TIME. Sometimes we need to just knuckle down and get on with it. Just not for a full year...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyway I became somewhat disillusioned with my employer and, truthfully, Northern Ireland. I like other people to be excited about the stuff I preach but I felt there was a lot of disinterest and empty words. This annoyed me and I guess I just started pushing harder, which I guess made me look quite angry and pushy. This obviously wouldn't help. When I looked outside of my company - Northern Ireland didn't seem that much better. So I felt a bit out of place and I had 2 choices ahead of me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Up sticks and go somewhere that I felt would be more receptive to my extreme nerdyness and desire to share it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stick around, my company and Northern Ireland and try and make a difference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;I chose the second, not being to be hero or anything but for more pragmatic reasons,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My wife got pregnant again (due soon yay!), the economy is terrible and it would be too much of a risk right now&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If I stayed in Northern Ireland, or even Ireland, I don't believe there is any other company that would support me (aka let me get away with) the things I do. I'm not the most predictable of sorts. I work weird hours and do strange things. &lt;a href="http://www.kainos.com"&gt;Kainos&lt;/a&gt; have always been there for me and supported me. Having done interviews with people from various levels from various other companies the state of other IT firms makes me seethe with anger.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is better to invest in people and risk them leaving than to not invest in them and risk them staying&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;So I start 2012 with a big challenge set for myself. That sounds about right. The more I think about &lt;a href="http://www.kainos.com"&gt;Kainos&lt;/a&gt;, my employer, deserves more credit than I give it. We have been in a space thats been all about big business types with big enterprisey solutions and delivered well. It's not an area that exactly screams enthusiasm and I think it will take a while to draw people out of that kind of insular thinking. &lt;a href="http://www.kainos.com"&gt;Kainos&lt;/a&gt; certainly seems to be better than most in this area. Now enough gushing about &lt;a href="http://www.kainos.com"&gt;Kainos&lt;/a&gt; (who are hiring BTW)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;2011 (The Good Parts)&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;OK OK 2011 wasn't all sob stories and dullness some really cool things happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My CodeSlice initiative in work (meet at least once a month, talk nerdy things, get &lt;a href="http://www.kainos.com"&gt;Kainos&lt;/a&gt; to pay for free pizza) didn't die. In fact in the hands of one of my colleagues, Jonny Holmes, it flourished. Attendence was never HUGE but it was consistent and varied. May long this tradition continue and hopefully we can expand it..&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I organised and participated in not one but two hackathons (internally). Once again &lt;a href="http://www.kainos.com"&gt;Kainos&lt;/a&gt; covered the costs for our weekend long hack sessions. Turnout was decent (about 8-12 people) with all types turning up - managers, placement students, technical architects etc. The experience was enough for me - which is a clever way of saying the end products weren't as good as envisaged. But we drew so many valuable lessons that the second one was infinitely more successful that the first - live and learn! And, oh lord, the plans I have for the first half of 2012 around hackathons are going to be legendary!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I talked, and not just to myself but to real people, real people who were not paid to be there! I talked, outside of work, a total of three times. I know the number isn't huge but it was late on in the year before I decided to get out there. Already topped that number for 2012 and the year hasn't started. Double figures would be good next year thank you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I attended &lt;a href="http://gotocon.com/amsterdam-2011/"&gt;GOTO Amsterdam&lt;/a&gt; were I got to meet a lot of people I have deemed awesome (because they are). Being in rooms with like minded people (who are generally much smarter than me) saying things that make you realise you are not insane for thinking things could be better really strengthens your beliefs!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shared more. All the stuff above I did because I wanted to get my thoughts out there - I wanted to be educated as well as educate. I was happy to look like a fool if it meant I didn't look like a fool later. Thats hard for an introvert but damn it I gave it my best shot. I know people, the one who only know me through my writing on &lt;a href="http://yammer.com"&gt;Yammer&lt;/a&gt; or half-read blog post, think I am a purist (I'm not - perfect is the enemy of better), or angry (not me, frustrated at times but never angry), or opinionated (openly opinionated perhaps) or even annoyed that everyone isn't dancing the happy geek dance like myself (as long as I'm not dancing alone on the dance floor like a sleazy old man stalking girls half his age I'm happy). Thats fine. People reckon I risk detracting from the message I am trying to communicate. Fair enough. Perhaps I need to tone it down sometimes - but I can't see that happening - it's no in my nature. I think it's better that people see me as a purist and take some of my ideas away rather than being half-assed and them not taking anything on board! It's inevitable that when I try and challenge peoples conceptions of technical things, especially in the open, it's going to leave a sour taste in some peoples mouths. But thats how I roll and thats how it should be. Sorry but there is more on the way. But I take as good as I give so come at me bros!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Won a years to subscription to &lt;a href="http://tekpub.com"&gt;Tekpub&lt;/a&gt; on Christmas Day thanks Rob 'Santa Clause' Conrey.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put my foot in it a few times. Yeah sounds odd I am classing this as a good thing but Scott Hanselman gave me permission, and I &lt;a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/BestPracticesForIndividualContribution.aspx"&gt;quote&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chris Sells told me once, If you're not getting in trouble with your boss at least twice a year, you're likely not pushing the envelope hard enough. Two slaps a year might be the cost for 10 successes. If you're not moving forward, well, you're not moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h2&gt;2012 (More like 20AWESOME! AMIRITE!)&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;So enough dwelling in the past - how am I going to make 2012 be the awesomest? Well thats easy - &lt;strong&gt;set some real fecking goals&lt;/strong&gt;. I failed to do that last year (outside of my typical career goals during my annual reviews of course) and ended up coasting in parts. Not next year - hells no. I got me a bucket list (stuff to do before the year dies - not me - unless that comes first - oh god I never thought of that). TO THE LIST!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;2012 Bucket List (In No Particular Order)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Release a screencast&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Release a game&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Appalachian Trail&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://givecampni.org.uk"&gt;GiveCamp NI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talk/Present as often as possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn a new language&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contribute more to OSS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;So let me explain some of these, as I am sure they mean sweet FA to some of you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Release a Screencast&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;A lot of my blog posts last year were a kind of "Introduction to Technology X" and I think that sort of knowledge can be better shared via video and real coding. Coupled with my desire to go a bit deeper in my technical posts but always getting distracted with other blog posts I think 2012 is the year I try my hand at producing a real life proper screencast (or perhaps a series). With decent production values and what not. The topic? Well I am currently thinking &lt;a href="http://nancyfx.org"&gt;Nancy&lt;/a&gt; but I need to really get my head around it a lot than I already do - but thats fine. Time will tell on that one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Release a Game&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Game programming is an area I've failed to venture into and I feel it is about time. I wan't to do something really simple, something mobiley possibly using &lt;a href="http://impactjs.com/"&gt;ImpactJS&lt;/a&gt; because it interests me. I'd like to release said game into an app store as well - just to watch it get flamed and to say "I've done it"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Appalachian Trail&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a codename for a current unfunded project of mine. The goal is to get a more fuller understanding of the spectrum of mobile development approaches, platforms and technologies. So simply put generate a bunch of super simple (though still useful) app ideas and using every conceivable type of technology from native to web and all in-between deliver decent quality apps across all the major platforms through hackathons, team challenges, school and university outreach, app camps etc..&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sounds awesome doesn't it?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;GiveCamp NI&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;GiveCamp was founded by Microsoft Developer Evangelist, Chris Koenig, in Dallas, Texas in 2007. His vision was to bring together passionate developers and local charitable organisations for an entire weekend, and see what would happen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In late 2012 GiveCamp is coming to Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thats what the &lt;a href="http://givecampni.org.uk/"&gt;official site&lt;/a&gt; says (I should know I put it there). So late next year we will run GiveCamp for the first time in Northern Ireland. A weekend long charity focused public hackathon. It's going to be a belter!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Talk/Present as often as possible&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I enjoy talking about nerdy things. I got a taste for it last year when I went public (having been talking internally to &lt;a href="http://www.kainos.com"&gt;Kainos&lt;/a&gt; staff for years) and in 2012 I really want to get out there as much as possible. I find it an amazing way for me to learn as well as understand whats going on in the industry. So far I am speaking in &lt;a href="http://dublinalt.net/2011/12/14/january-meetup-calling-all-mobile-devs/"&gt;Dublin in January&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.devweek.com/"&gt;Devweek in London&lt;/a&gt; and a few other un-announced venues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BTW if anyone can recommend conferences I should pitch for, or want me to come over and talk about anything in the .NET/JavaScript/Mobie world(s) (see my blog for the kind of thing I know about) - let me know!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Learn a new language&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Everyone says this one right? Yeah so I spent last year looking at node.js and Ruby and I think it's time to get out of my safe - I'm thinking F# - yeah that sounds sweet!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Contribute more to OSS&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I head-dived into OSS .NET last year and loved it. Many people see .NET as a very restricted, Microsoft led platform were every modern web-app is MVC3 with Entity Framework and WCF rules the web service world. Thats total bull. .NET has a very vibrant, very active OSS community. There is almost no need to use any MS technology ever. But lets not forget MS have really started to embrace and support OSS in a big way. Lets hope that trend continues!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;In Summary&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Boooo to 2011, Yay to 2012. See you around the same time next year when I have another failful year and promising myself a better one in 2013 :-P&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Out with the old...</title><updated>Fri Nov 25 00:00:00 UTC 2011</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2011/11/25/out-with-the-old-dot-dot-dot/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:Out with the old...</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;... in with the new. So I've started rolling out my new site, expect somethings to be slightly broken as images and whatnot have been moved around. Spent a day or two designing a new site that was similar to the old one but slightly better. Eventually got frustrated at my inability to do any sort of graphical design and went the &lt;a href="http://octopress.org"&gt;Octopress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still a few things to tweak, possibly add a splash of colour around the place and give it a bit more life. Also apologies to people who subscribe to my feed - looks like the new feed has pushed all the old posts out as new. But hey they are worth reading twice!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>GiveCamp Northern Ireland 2012</title><updated>Thu Nov 03 00:00:00 UTC 2011</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2011/11/03/givecamp-northern-ireland-2012/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:GiveCamp Northern Ireland 2012</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://givecampni.org.uk/assets/img/givecamp-large-logo.png" alt="GiveCamp" _="_" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://givecampni.org.uk/"&gt;http://givecampni.org.uk/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aint no backing out now son! In 2012 there is going to be a Northern Ireland based &lt;a href="http://givecamp.org"&gt;GiveCamp&lt;/a&gt;. The "Register Your Interest" placeholder site is now live at &lt;a href="http://givecampni.org.uk/"&gt;http://givecampni.org.uk/&lt;/a&gt; so if everyone can start spreading the word and getting excited that would be super awesome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Any tips, advice or help at this point is also really welcome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let the fun begin....&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Personal Systems of (Dis)Organisation</title><updated>Tue Sep 20 23:00:00 UTC 2011</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2011/09/20/personal-systems-of-dis-organisation/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:Personal Systems of (Dis)Organisation</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the outside people probably regard me as a typically chaotic person. My desk is a mess, I'm not mad keen on the whole shaving thing, my writing is terrible and I am generally not where people expect me to be at any particular time. But there is, more often than not, a workflow that works for me hidden deep down in the chaos. Most people stick to one or two way to organise themselves (Todo Lists, pen and paper, iPad etc.). Not me. I'm still trying to find some sort of process that fits well with me but I'm starting to think that perhaps that actually is my process. I move from different mediums and tools quite a lot. Doing this isn't always easy given some tools just natrually try and lock you in. My current workflow involves a few tools,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pen and paper (Work only). Nothing beats its it immediate and short term loggin of free form information. I have strict rules around it though.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blank paper - no lines or binder holes or headers. I guess I subconciouslly view this a restriction perhaps?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Black pen (with a bit of red). I've totally gone off blue pen - it makes my notes look messy (they are though). Pencil has been overtaken by the black ink pen these days though I am not sure why&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.wunderlist.com/"&gt;Wunderlist&lt;/a&gt;. List management. Cloud syncing. Free. I moved from &lt;a href="http://culturedcode.com/things/"&gt;Things.app&lt;/a&gt; when I realised they just don't seem to listen to their customers. Cloud synching is essential. Wunderlist offers me a cross platform and web based solution for doing everything I need quickly. I use this for medium-longer term "listable" tasks such as,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Project Deliverables&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;General day to day work tasks (though not shopping lists - see later)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Things to blog about&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wish lists for presentas and books and things (shared with family who also do the same thing)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;iOS 5's Reminders app. Yeah ANOTHER list manager. This one is for very short time lists such as shopping lists. I find polluting Wunderlist with this sort of list very annoying. I don't use it that often but it's the best app I find for ultra fast entry of lists.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://trello.com/"&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt;. The latest addition to my supposed system. It's essentially a multi-level list system. Kind of like a cross between a Kanban board and a Todo list application. I am currently using this for more and more things. Essentially higher level list management that makes more sense to have a pseudo workflow or a board to collect realted lists and collaborate with others. The key to this one is everything becomes more collaborative but it's much less restictive than something like AgileZen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Books (To Read, Reading, Finished)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hackathon Voting (Ideas, Timings, Dates, Objectives etc). Allows a bunch of people to vote and discuss relevant things for the next hackathon. We also use checklists for things we need to prepare in advance etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;House renovations (one list per room). Shared between my wife and myself.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://agilezen.com/"&gt;AgileZen&lt;/a&gt;. Amazing site for Kanban and Scrum. Essentially a Kanban board with enough flexbility/features that means we can tailor the workflow to suit the needs of the project and team. I use this for work projects where feedback on times and bottlenecks is essential. Can't say enough great things about this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whiteboard - Ultra transient information. I use this during real time &lt;strong&gt;brain thinking&lt;/strong&gt; sessions. An old friend remareked that the process of getting out of your chair and picking up a pen changes the way you think and creates a more open environment for ideas. Generally items on the whiteboard last a couple of minutes. Anything important can be photographed and sent to Evernote or email. I do my best work at a whiteboard. If I am blanking I get up and start doodling - inspiration eventually comes. Currently there is a picture of Silos (pronounced Sigh Loss) - The Evil Data Overlord - makes sense to me. &lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/blog/silos.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.evernote.com/"&gt;Evernote&lt;/a&gt;. Online storage of notes useful for indexing and searching. To be honest - more information goes into this than comes out but it has saved my neck a few times with information I thought irrelevant. I moved from OneNote because there was no suitable OneNote client for the devices I use. Oh and I own a Mac.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.tripit.com/"&gt;TripIt&lt;/a&gt;. I'm travelling a bit more these days and it is always nice to have all the necessary information in one place that actually assists planning by proving maps and schedules. Assistive metasites are the future!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fridge (one of those cold things in your kitchen) - My materialised Kanban board at home that I use for "hobby" activities when I am off work to let my wife know what I am up to and plan accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Calendar - Outlook synched to Google and available on all devices. I don't use this directly but other people do and I follow the instructions people send to me (if I think it's worth my time).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Email - Most disorganised but oft used medium for retrieving information (usually once and discarded or archived to never be accessed again)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;So you see I have got a lot of stuff in a lot of places but luckily important information is exactly where I need it. It may not seem sane or organised but for some reason it is to me - or maybe this is very very normal?&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Talking at DDD North and Belfast</title><updated>Mon Sep 19 23:00:00 UTC 2011</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2011/09/19/talking-at-ddd-north-and-belfast/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:Talking at DDD North and Belfast</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The start of October is going to be a busy time for me - in a good way. The first weekend I'll be doing two talks at &lt;a href="http://developerdeveloperdeveloper.com/dddie11/Schedule.aspx"&gt;DeveloperDeveloperDeveloper in Belfast&lt;/a&gt; and the following week I'll be skipping over to Sunderland (first time there) do do another talk for &lt;a href="http://developerdeveloperdeveloper.com/north/Schedule.aspx"&gt;DeveloperDeveloperDeveloper North&lt;/a&gt;. I've been lucky enough to land the same presentation for both DDD Belfast and DD North which means I have slightly less to prepare. Not that it will be a drop in quality in anyway - no siree.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the interested folk the two talks are outlined below. The titles and synopsis are fairly childish/over-sensationalised (delete as you see fit) but thats the way I roll. My opinion enjoys being passed around and so my talks will feature a heavy dose of it - with all necessary disclaimers attached. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For both events I'll be covering,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;h1&gt;refORM: Death to ORMs in .NET&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data Access is a difficult area to master. There are plenty of frameworks such as Entity Framework, NHibernate, i/myBatis. These frameworks attempt to make data access simpler but while these products are widely used they can lead to leaky abstractions forcing us to work around constraints of the technology or introduce the nightmare of trying to figure out what is happening deep down in the frameworks internals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this session we will look at the various lightweight alternatives and the advantages they offer as well as provide rationale about why the more heavyweight approach isn't always the best approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;And for DDD Belfast only,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;h1&gt;CoffeeScript the Awesome&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;CoffeeScript - "a little language that compiles into JavaScript" has been making a lot of noise in the web community with its inclusion in Ruby on Rail v3 and its swift rise in popularity on Github.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This session will look at the benefits this language brings over the native JavaScript alternative, the syntactical double rainbow it creates, the problems you'll face and of course how you can actually use it in different technology stacks such as Ruby, node.js, .NET and Java.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've never really undertaken sessions of this size before (mostly internal or for a customer) so it's going to be a cracking experience. Hopefully people get as much out of these sessions as I will. I'll have whatever resources up after the events as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;See you there (maybe).&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Screencasts Galore!  More or less.</title><updated>Thu May 19 23:00:00 UTC 2011</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2011/05/19/screencasts-galore-more-or-less/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:Screencasts Galore!  More or less.</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SCREEEEEEEEEEEEEEEEEEEEEEENCASTS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GALORE&lt;/span&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So I unveiled the new &lt;a href="/screencasts"&gt;screencasts&lt;/a&gt; section of the site. Can you guess whats in it? Those who said "screencasts" you can have a nice non-patronising pat on the head. The rest of you. for shame. Tut tut.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyways I wanted to start a series of short &lt;a href="/screencasts"&gt;screencasts&lt;/a&gt; that will provide a practical view of the .&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NET&lt;/span&gt; Micro Web Framework series. So far I've managed to cover the basics of &lt;a href="http://jessicafx.org"&gt;Jessica&lt;/a&gt; but there is more to come.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>The First Day of the Rest of My Life</title><updated>Sun May 15 23:00:00 UTC 2011</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2011/05/15/the-first-day-of-the-rest-of-my-life/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:The First Day of the Rest of My Life</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Move complete, more or less. Still a few broken images and stuff but like the unpacked boxes of a new house these will probably remain that way until about next year or so. Decent enough weekend project all in. For anyone who's interested in what's went on under the hood - read on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Abandoning Posterous&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://posterous.com"&gt;Posterous&lt;/a&gt; is great as a simple blogging platform but in terms of giving me exactly what I wanted at any point in time &lt;a href="http://posterous.com"&gt;Posterous&lt;/a&gt; and most other platforms didn't give me exactly what I wanted (I am quite a demanding character I guess).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was doing some research on .&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NET&lt;/span&gt; Micro Web Frameworks and came across &lt;a href="http://jessicafx.org"&gt;Jessica&lt;/a&gt; which was created and maintained by &lt;a href="http://tombell.org.uk"&gt;Tom Bell&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Browsing Toms &lt;a href="http://github.com/tombell"&gt;github repo&lt;/a&gt; I discovered he prodced his site using &lt;a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; a Ruby based static site generator and I knew I had to have it! So I ripped off Toms nice design, uglified it with my own tweaks and what you see now is the finished site. This site is also mirroed on &lt;a href="http://kouphax.github.com"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; but some of the functions (category pages) are missing due to some custom generators that the Github Jekyll instance doesn't run.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is more to be deployed but I'd rather polish what I have before pushing more stuff out. I've tinkered with Project page generation, &lt;a href="https://github.com/schacon/showoff"&gt;Showoff&lt;/a&gt; for presentations and a few other things that will appear over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Domain Name&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seriously - how couldn't I go for a shiny web 2.0 ultra elite domain name given the chance? &lt;a href="http://gandi.net"&gt;Gandi.net&lt;/a&gt; was recommended to me and I must admit the set up was fairly painless and their admin panel stuff is very nice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Appharbor&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Currently my static site is hosted on &lt;a href="http://appharbor.com"&gt;appharbor&lt;/a&gt;. Appharbor is awesome. Typically I've used it to spin up quick demos and stuff and the simplicity of doing a &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt; to deploy your new version is like a dream (especially given the heavy handed approach of Azure).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Thats It&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not sure that anyone cares about this sort of stuff but I just want to take my new process for a spin anyway. Any questions - let me know.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>On The Move</title><updated>Fri May 13 23:00:00 UTC 2011</updated><author><name>James Hughes</name></author><link href="https://yobriefca.se/blog/2011/05/13/on-the-move/"></link><id>urn:yobriefca-se:feed:post:On The Move</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So I've decided to go ahead and move away from &lt;a href="http://yobriefcase.posterous.com"&gt;Posterous&lt;/a&gt; - the call of &lt;a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; was just too much. I've migrated a lot of my content but there is some dodgy formatting and plenty of missing images so I am in the process of sorting everything out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also thanks to &lt;a href="http://tombell.org.uk"&gt;Tom Bell&lt;/a&gt; for letting me use his template.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>